[Music]
all right hello everyone welcome to
acton-flab
livestream number 41.2
it's april 13th 2022.
so welcome to the actin flap we're a
participatory online lab that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links on this slide
this is recorded and an archived live
stream so please provide us with
feedback so that we can be improving on
our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following good
video etiquette for livestream and dean
and blue thanks a ton for joining
check out activeinference.org
to learn more about what the acting lab
is up to and how you can participate
today in
number 41.2 we are going to have our
third
discussion on the paper extended active
inference
constructing predictive cognition beyond
skulls by axel constant andy clark
michael kirchoff and carl fristen
we had a zero video
where we took a first pass a first coat
of paint on this paper
overviewed some of their distinctions
and their background and some context
and then we had a fun dot one last week
with all of us here and we went down a
few different paths
and
all i can say is with trust and glue
of
all of
us here and those who are watching live
who are welcome to write questions in
the live chat i think we'll get
somewhere pretty cool in the next two
hours but can't even know what shape it
will be then
so we can just start by saying hello and
then
we can
[Music]
pick up where we've left off
or we can go in any other direction so
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california and i think the part that i'm
looking most forward to exploring today
is that trust and glue and how do we
trust and glue
appropriately or adaptively and i'll
pass to d
thanks daniel i'm dean i'm in british
columbia at the moment
um i really like where you and blue
were
were going with this
um once i signed off last week and i was
particularly
interested in the idea of is the answer
in the question
because i thought that was a an
interesting
way of maybe looking at is there an
extended active inference component to
that so maybe you'll pick that thread up
again today i'll pass it to blue
i am blue i'm a researcher in new mexico
and
yeah trust and glue or um
you know what kind of improvisational
context do we use this extended active
inference like where is this kind of
um
thing necessary functional where do we
see it like what kinds of environments
maybe highlight extended active
inference that'd be interesting for me
to explore
awesome
so we have a few different
aspects we can
talk and return to some formalisms about
how are the equations connected
internally how are the formalisms
connected to one another how are the
extended active inference formalisms
framed in this paper connected to
earlier
or now that some time has passed since
the publication later formalisms in
active inference how are they connected
to the ideas that we've been discussing
we have
questions and answers
or answers and questions
what does that look like in the context
of extended active inference
perception
action learning teaching applying
finding discovering
a lot of ing
verbs and that is
hiding or
somehow
intertwined with this
question which is always
in the backdrop or the pre-drop or stage
right or something like that
with what takes us from a regime of
attention
or regime of intention
towards
active inference itself
and some specific model
so
where to go i think the most structured
of the operations here is to remind
ourselves of the formalisms and the
figures and then maybe we can come back
to any of these as we see does that
sound good
okay
their equation one
is a
fairly typical
restatement of
bayes theorem so we won't dwell too much
on that
but it is relating to the decomposition
of a joint model
of
both observations and inferred latent
causes and the total model contains both
of those
yet it's able to be decomposed in some
amenable ways
equation 2
using variational inference one can
invert the likelihood in equation one
the probability of the hidden states
conditioned on observation
to approximate the posterior probability
of causes once a sensation has been
sampled
so
is this a twist dean
or what kind of inversion are we talking
about here when we go from thinking
about
the likelihood which is like the
probability of
there being a lightning strike
conditioned upon
what we actually observed
and that is now flipping to what are the
causes
given the sensation
well
here's a here's a question for both of
you
is there such a thing as a group
sensation
i mean if we if we think of it i mean
it's seldom that we would consider
ourselves
as a proportion of a
larger volume of energy when we find
ourselves in these contexts
and in these cultures
um
so what happens when we invert that idea
i'm one pie
in a whole collection of pies at a pie
shop
to
i'm some proportion
of
of a larger energy set
and then what are the implications of
that in terms of the kind of evidence
that i can or cannot gather
so that's my question for both of you
because you guys probably can answer
that better than i can
so i think we definitely experience
group sensation
um i think about like
the countries that are being bombed
right now and i think about like the
countries that when a tsunami hits like
there is definitely a group felt sense
of like terror that's like a group
sensation but also even on like a
positive note like i think about like
huge concerts and it's like a bunch of
people really having fun and that's kind
of another like group
sensation um like even like yeah those
kinds of
um
group things or even like large
meditation retreats is like another good
example of like a group sensation and it
does kind of get like
amplified or it feels like the sensation
is like going through a megaphone when
you know you're experiencing it with
5000 people or something like that so in
my experience
and does that change the formalism
like i mean i think we can identify it
but does that change the math or the way
that we measure that
base it based on the source of
affective
sensing within within one agent versus
that collective
measure i think i think it just changes
where we put the blanket
doesn't change the math though
i think it just changes where we put the
blanket like like so so if you have a
bigger blanket you know there's there's
more components
um you know like you would separate the
group of people that are experiencing
the concert from a group of people that
are about to experience a tsunami you
know there's like a huge partition and
it's it's
the same as separating two different
people mathematically it's just
separating groups of people like as
mathematically we are groups of
cells tissues organs so i think that the
the only difference is just what's under
that markov blanket
all right a few cool
points to make so
you asked about group sensations
and if we were in a
unidirectional signa signal processing
paradigm
the question could be approached like
what are the outside signals that come
in and how do those diffuse through the
group
what does that look like when
we've taken a step towards thinking
about perception as inference as a
generative inference so what are groups
expecting
so what is the same way that we talk
about perception cognition and affect
and memory anticipation planning as
inference of entities
what does it mean for the group to not
just be passively receiving sensations
but to be
engaged in active inference so that's
going to be a
a
big question and i'll leave it for
another brief break to write out a few
more options here but i think what blue
said about it depends on where the
blanket is drawn or how the model is
phrased relates to the composability of
active inference and the way that it's
kind of like
blocks
that play nice together laterally
as well as in a nested fashion
including
a nice little tuck at the end so let me
explain by what i mean there
the way that they interact laterally is
it's a framework that allows you to
simulate one ant or many ants because
one can just have
more and more entities in the same
lateral level or scale that are
interacting with the same environment
and or with each other whether that's
like direct contact or with
communication because all that one needs
to specify is the entity model and then
their
perception their oom felt basically and
their action selection like their
affordances so if we know
where where the blanket is
that was the system of interest that's
the entity the ant and then what goes
both directions
that
allows composability of a thousand ants
just like one but then the key piece
with the nesting
is
even if we only
write down
a single layer active model so the mouse
in the t maze or just a single layer
it's not a deep nested
hierarchical model
we can actually still interpret
that
graphical model
as
abstracting or receiving
other models that we didn't directly
formalize
um
so it was discussed in in the textbook
and in other sources of like we could
make an active inference model of one
brain region with the inputs as sense
states and the outputs as action states
and then in that single brain region
model
those input states
it can just be like that's where
the black box is there's just
um an inability to actually do modeling
on the details of what's coming in we're
just going to leave it at some sort of
stochastic process coming in
so it kind of like tucks all the
uncertainty
away
into
this hidden little corner and then we're
going to interface with that uncertainty
as it becomes
recognized by the system of interest or
one could make another model of that
second brain region and it could have
its own perception action states but
then that too
would have inputs coming from elsewhere
and actions going elsewhere so i think
there's probably more to unpack and
explore here but this
hopefully speaks to the composability of
active inference models to implicitly
contain nested subsystems like we could
do an active inference model of a person
and recognize that they consist of
organs and cells and organelles and
go all the way down to however small
and
we can compose down and dig down
or compose up as the extended
perspective hopefully will have us look
at
but
we get to be making our
single layer model
implicitly
within a more composable structure
than many other families of modeling
might allow for
so that might give a ability to compare
alternative ways of looking at
multi-scale extended systems
but it will be more like a comparison of
relative free energies or relative model
fits
rather than some sort of ad hoc
comparison that we're applying based
upon
a desire for simplicity or desire for to
see this many levels
i wonder in the sense that i understand
that
you can have the
you can have the single land and you can
you can find the average in the eco evo
devo as you pointed out in
in
earlier versions of this set of
of um live streams
and you can also look at the entire
colony
and look at it and find an average of
its behavior over hiko evo and devo as
well
but that's why i'm not i'm not
questioning whether or not
the
if you use if you use one type of math
and you just decide which
which
partition you're going to make that
that's going to kick out a certain
expected kind of
of average what i'm what i'm
kind of curious about is
um
in the synchronicity question so we all
go to the concert for example
we all anticipate because this is the
anticipatory part we all anticipate
having a good time how do we build that
into
what the actual result is when we all
start singing along to the chorus
because i don't know
i don't know if there's a math for that
quite yet
and that's all i'm basically asking i'm
not i'm not questioning the formalism
per se i'm just saying if we build up
how does that affect
what the equations are telling us versus
if we as you said daniel
maybe collapse down
and what the math tells us there there's
going to be an average that gets kicked
out so
not arguing
i'm not ignoring that i'm just saying i
think there is an anticipatory piece to
this
when we're talking about extended active
inference and what we should be able to
anticipate what that surprisal should be
and what ends up happening when
um
those external controls in terms of
rules
play their part and what each
individual's heuristics that they bring
to the collective play their part and
what that how that all sort of
transpires into something which can be
measured and other parts of which may
still be
way too untractable that's all
blue any thoughts
no i i think uh
i don't know i said what i
needed to say i think um
it scales differently for for me than
how dean perceives it i think
i'm gonna bring in another
resource here so this is from the uh
the 2021 paper felix scholler mark
miller roy salomon and carl fristen
and it's trust as extended control human
machine interactions as active inference
so
staying on this trust and glue and
extended anticipatory theme
so here is one figure that they have
okay
on the left side is a
uni dimensional scalar perspective on
trust
so this is like from zero to ten or one
could think that zero is the threshold
pass through zero rather than passing
through five
do not collect two hundred dollars on
your way through five but you might on
the way through zero
and we have negative trust
as well as like positive complete trust
with
various associations we could make like
having aligned interest or um shared
affection
they then expand
that
uni-dimensional
perspective into like a two-dimensional
perspective on trust
and they separate out the x-axis and the
y-axis as being trustworthiness and
trust and we've been talking about glue
and trust so let's keep the glue and
trust
rattling around as we think about this
later work which
undoubtedly is building upon the current
paper we're discussing
and so
on the y equals x line
where the trust and the trustworthiness
evaluations are equivalent that is where
you have justified trust
meaning like high sense of trust felt
sense of trust in a trustworthy system i
believe the glue is strong and the glue
is manifestly strong i believe the glue
is weak and it's breaking all the time
so that's on the y equals x line and
that's like a manifold which is to say a
lower dimensional line in a higher
dimensional state space that actually is
this uni-dimensional one so we can
imagine that being like at an angle and
being the y equals x line
what is opening it up into multiple
dimensions allow us to talk about
well
it's
allowing
other quadrants to be explored where the
perceived sense of trust may differ
from the
objective or the relational
trust
and so it's sort of like separating out
cognitive versus the behavioral
dimensions of trust like would you
rather
be the person that people behaviorally
trust like they give their keys to you
but then they're always having the
sentiment
or having the communications that that
person's untrustworthy
or would you rather have the lip service
or the cognitive lip service of people
thinking and feeling and maybe even
speaking like they trust you but then
when it comes down to it there's no
actual behavioral trust there so they
explored that in the context of
human robotic interactions and
technology
so then let's just look at the second
one and then it'll be awesome to hear
what you two think or anyone in the chat
here they're looking at
generations of technology
along with their adoption curves
and the ways in which they enable
empowerment
and so the three rows here
are like the sort of mobility
genre
of the legs embodied
moving into the extended and then
cultured with like the horses and the
cars there's like a weaponry genre or a
sport hunting
for those who want to
and then there's a navigation and
orientation which even came up in our
discussion last time about
cloud-based map services and how that
leads to changes like in our spatial
navigation and especially as we'll be
exploring in 42 upcoming
what if the neurobiology of navigation
is deeply intrinsic to ourselves so what
is actually happening to ourselves
as the navigational technology
becomes something that we trust
something that we
glue to and so here they're just showing
that there's this um spiral
of increasing empowerment like an
individual who's in the v3 tech stack
here
has certain
constraints and affordances and just
simply differences not even
better except on specifically defined
axes
than those in the v1 tech stack so
where do some of these representations
or points that are raised in the later
shoulder paper
speak to either of you
do you have something to happen to that
blue
so i'm not like really getting this
empowerment time adoption like without
reading the paper it's just like not
clicking for me
so i have to i guess catch up um in this
trust versus extended control
yes totally agreeing and um definitely
the the real time
uh
interpretation is um
non-trivial so let's just look at what
they defined there
to measure the amount of control or
influence an agent has and perceives
klubin at all proposed the concept of
empowerment empowerment is a property of
self-organized adaptive systems and is a
function of the agent perception action
loop
more specifically the relation between
sensors and actuators of the organism as
induced by interactions between the
environment and the agent's morphology
so this goes back to like the definition
of agency and where we were talking
about empowerment as like a definable
measurable metric on a live stream
recently
you remember that now it's starting to
kind of click in
um
but but we were talking about that
like the um capacity of an entity to
realize their preferences
like you can have all the preferences in
the world on a given on the temperature
of
the that day but on that dimension
one's empowerment like their capacity
for action selection
to have
impact a causal impact
on
what is being preferred
that is minimal
versus one can be empowered and um not
even care
and they could have the power to to
modify something and yet not
approach that potentially seriously
yeah so it's clicking now it's making a
little bit more um sense but i'm still
not really getting this graph
the the um
i understand like empowerment over
time i guess
i mean
like if you think about a graph of a
human we become more empowered we're
like a
uh inverted parabola right so like we
become more empowered as time goes on
and then less empowered as we you know
age and
become less able to care for ourselves
we're unable at the beginning and then
we max empowerment and then like least
empowerment towards the end of our life
or or if we live to be you know 110 or
whatever not always true the end of life
gets a little weird it's a wiggly trail
off line
that that reminds me of um
the classic riddle
what has
four legs in the morning
two legs in the midday and then three
legs at night
it's a person
yeah
and then also um
let's look at what they mean by these
like flex because there's a few other
pieces of course that this paper is um
bringing in and then we'll kind of
return to the trust and glue of the
constant at all
so
of course it's a simplification
the important idea here is that
the inflection point flex
indicating the start of technological
decay
reflects the abandoned rate of a
practice as the experience of better
predicted slopes of extended
technological engagement
lead to disengagement of non-extended
approaches
cars replace horses replacing legs
old slopes are less than expected
and so unsatisfactory as compared to new
ones
so it's a
uh technology adoption
model
and often we just see the s-curve part
of the adoption and people will say like
well here's how fast telegraph was
adopted then the radio then the tv then
the internet and so one can look at
these s-curves of adoption and sometimes
they like start low they go up and then
they flatten out and then it's sort of
like look the technology's at 100
adoption
this is also showing not just the rise
of empire but the decline
where we're seeing the
retraction of use from a given
technology and isn't it funny that we
may have actually you know used our legs
less
as other technologies come into play
like just the steps per day
so we have each of these technologies
stacks
that they're modeling here have like a
curve of adoption
and also a curve by which they're no
longer in use
with many simplifications as people can
hopefully charitably interpret
and what they're pointing to
is actually that the inflection point
of the next generation
when things are like when it's moving as
fast adoption is increasing as fast as
it's going to increase for this new tech
occurs
basically
it must be occurring during the decline
the peak or the decline phase
of the previous generation of glue
because
unless the technologies can be
coexisting in use but
they're looking a little bit more like
technologies that replace one another
so it's interesting here because
legs are actually glued to you
whereas like horses can wander away or
be stolen so there's like an
intermediate level of glue but like cars
are like you know or horses are like the
most likely to to go away and then cars
are you know not
they have no agency themselves so they
can kind of be glued a little bit more
tightly so horses are like the least
amount of glue and cars are like the
most amount of glue it's interesting
yes like
yes dean
so um
i have relatives who have a ranch in the
in the um
wine growing
um part of british columbia
and in a in a strange conversation
i asked my relative who has a number of
horses
would he ever consider
instead of people being
carted around in
many buses
from
winery to winery on a wine tour given
the proximity
to a number of
vineyards
would he ever consider
uh
taking
his
his horses and and putting a business
plan together around having people go
from vineyard to vineyard on horseback
and he laughed me off in a like in a
heartbeat because he said no i think
that would be very dangerous people with
drinking too much wine and
and
trying to stay on their horse
but then he came back to me later on
and said i maybe i was too dismissive of
that
because of the novelty aspect of it and
if you could actually control
the nature of because he's got great
horses i've ridden on his horses a lot
but if you could actually control that
situation the novelty of that
means that the people that would
participate in that would actually be
doing something very unique and very
novel
and so that reversion back to something
that's not necessarily
seen as being something super efficient
is actually something that can be
something that's very attractive and
extend that generative model
now we haven't followed through on that
that was
that was mid pandemic
but just this conversation right here i
find it really well i
find it kind of disturbing because to
have all of that now come rushing back
a year and and
five months later
kind of tells me whoa what what hap
what's going on here but it's that it's
that
it's that sense that in the collective
extended act of inference in that
probability of what portion of a
population would actually find this
interesting instead of just dismissing
it out of hand and saying no that would
be a logistical nightmare
um
you incorporate base right you actually
see as well maybe there is a percentage
of the population that would actually
see this as something really unique as
long as it's not something that's
unmanageable right
so i had no idea that you were going to
bring this up i'd have no absolutely no
idea what the comparison is of
empowerment to the adoption uptake of
that particular offering but i do find
it really curious right now that it here
it comes again it's popping up again and
it's not a constructivist thing so much
as it's
holding open the idea that there is
not necessarily a whole bunch of people
that just want to
be
housed in a in a minivan
what's the what's the possibility then
so it's actually pretty interesting in
terms of this extended active inference
right it's not optimization in the in
the conventional sense of well we can
now get nine wineries in four hours
maybe it's a an all day thing and people
actually
tell all their friends what a great
experience they had
so you you look at the model a little
their generative model is inverted
i hate to break it to you dean but the
idea is not that novel
well there you go well so where i live
um i live like really pretty far out in
the middle of nowhere and there's one
bar
like within maybe a 25 mile radius
and people ride their horse to the bar
and there's hitches for the horse where
you can tie the horses outside uh i
drove daniel up that road so he knows
he's been he's driven right past it so
there's hitches where you can tie your
horse and to go to the bar and drink it
and people actually have been cited for
dwi on horseback um after leaving the
bar
also the the cinque terre is um amazing
uh a little series of five towns in
italy and there's no cars um i mean they
say that no cars there are these tiny
little baby like trash trucks and like
fedex delivery trucks but like there's
no roads that a car could actually drive
on just these little tiny like
car like things but you have to get you
have to arrive by boat or by train and
people take horseback from you know
through these five little towns that's
they do horse tours and wine it's a
five little towns that what they do is
make wine so like that's definitely like
a winery tour and there's a beautiful
beach and yeah it's really kind of nice
so so
maybe novel in the area and there's some
value always to that but uh i yeah i had
to bring up the the closest bar to my
house where there's horse hitches i'm
actually at the family dollar which is
like also the only store near where i
live i've seen people tie their horse to
like the handicapped parking signs in
the front of the store
classic two things one shout out for the
gelato in rio magiori
and two
i could just see
because i've been to the to the well i
haven't been in the french laundry but
that famous restaurant in napa
that's up from napa bit but but i never
saw
like
a dozen people riding by on their horses
but i could just imagine for the people
who are going there that wouldn't seem
out of place
so yeah
two shout outs
here's an interesting pattern so
let's
review figure 1 and 2 just briefly
because that's
that's one of the key contributions it's
also some of the formalism so
um we are
taking it fast but then we'll take it
slow
in figure one we saw the standard action
perception loop that we've seen in
different guises
where we have
perception and cognition
as being a process of
optimization and that is what the
variational approach enables
so that's what they write here um
variational inference converts an
inference problem into an optimization
problem articulated by equation three so
that's where we went from
the bayesian decomposition
into this variational approach
variational because there's this q
distribution that we control and we're
minimizing a divergence between a
distribution that we're in control of
that's simplified from a family that's
very tractable to study from this true
posterior which is inferred and then we
go from that variational phrasing of
this inversion to an optimization that
helps us solve it
that's what we're seeing in figure one
there's optimization happening at the
cognitive part of the partition and at
the action part
the sensory inputs are not being chosen
by the entity directly they can engage
in active inference to take action
selection that then brings
predictability and control to sensations
perceptual control theory however those
are not directly being controlled or
optimized so that was figure one and we
talked about how on the other side of
the table there still is this stochastic
dynamical equation
reflecting how external states depend on
their prior
states
and on action so we still have this
interactive
external states
with
potentially complex and self-reinforcing
dynamics that's emitting sense states
and so it goes in figure two
that gets brought into the extended
active inference space because now on
the other side of the table from our
star system of interest the brain here
is also something looking more like an
argument
of
previous external states and action
selection rather than looking more like
a stochastic differential equation so
now we have extended active inference
because there's like an adaptive
cognitive process happening on both
sides of the blanket
and that
provides this new interpretation
of what is crossing the boundary
as being joint self-evidencing and part
of a joint optimization process even if
these two
different arguments are quite different
from each other okay so that's also
where figure four came into play
the same way that figure one developed
into figure two from the
mirror active inference on the other
side of the table to the adaptive on the
other side of the table
in equation two we were looking at the
variational optimizable
approximation of figure one
and in equation four we're looking at
the variational
optimizable equation describing
basically figure two
let's return to our discussion on
trusting control and glue and tech and
all of this
even before there was spears if we were
gonna have v zero we could have
legs hands
and
some
embodied
navigational
onboard perspective so that's the pure
bioware
stack v0
and then
we can think about and it's not so clean
across these different um verticals of
technology
but the horse
for sure is like an adaptive active
entity like there is an intelligence on
the other side of the table when
somebody is
riding a horse
what's interesting is that
cars
may be
um
complex
however simple early cars were more like
a mere active inference entity i'm sure
they still
brought surprise and they broke and did
things that were like wacky and stuff
but it was kind of like
operating a motor
now
cars and technologies are actually
becoming increasingly
um
adaptive on the other side so let's
replace horses and v2 what if it was a
map like a paper map
a bow and arrow
and a skateboard
so those are all non-living
extended entities
and those are
one stack and then the next level is
like the technology is developing
but it still is um
[Music]
like that offloading rather than the
uploading like you can't punch the
person from 500 feet but you can
use the crossbow to do basically the
same transfer of kinetic
energy
and
with digital technology
digital models of cognition we're moving
into a place where like
the car the gun
the gps system
like
they might just say you can't do that
so that is
changing the nature of interaction with
technology
whereas like a trusty bow was one that
can be relied upon to be behave
predictably in a certain way
what is trust and glue
when
there are
when we're in the figure two worlds with
everything
here's the bow
and skateboard worlds
in figure one
and now
this is in like a
adaptive active setting
but
yeah blue
so i'm really reminded of um
the
pay phones and like i know you know dean
is old enough to remember but like
daniel what were you like five when they
had pay phones i'm just kidding
[Laughter]
so so i mean we you know
everywhere so we had a telephone we had
a telephone at home right like we could
trust it that if we were at home we
could connect with whoever we would want
to connect with
um and then you know there was all these
pay phone technologies like if you were
somewhere where there were people where
there was a gas station you could always
find a pay phone
and it's interesting like the you know
so we
we were okay being away from our home
phone but we had some trust that
somewhere we could find a phone to
connect with people if we needed to
right
but we still couldn't connect with them
unless they were at their house there
was this other weird like
looped component and then you know you
don't see a payphone now at all like the
last time i saw when i took a picture of
it
because it's like such an anomalous
thing i mean they just don't exist
anymore because there's some you know
everyone trusts that they'll have a
phone and yeah if your phone battery
dies it's okay you trust that you'll be
able to charge it you know in your car
or you get a battery pack or you have a
solar battery pack i have one of those
it's great um but so so you trust that
you'll be able to connect even if you
don't have your phone someone will have
a phone right so like you know if you're
in a car accident have no cell phone
someone will stop and you can use their
phone so there's always this but it's
it's interesting this level of of
you know trust and the ability to
communicate with others and then what
does that do to us cognitively like if
we you know
uh can you check the fridge hon did i
leave do we need milk like you know can
you call your house and find out like
it's interesting so i wonder how much
more preparation we used to do
without this ability to communicate
broadly like at the push of a button or
you know 10 buttons or whatever
b
can i just build on that for a second so
a couple of things um
and if we're going to if we're gonna do
it around the world thing
there are places still in the world
where
although there's a whole bunch of people
that have got their own device there's
still lots and lots of pay phones right
so we we don't see them necessarily in
our cognitive niche but
i can think i can think of central
american countries that i visited
recently and i'm going to be visiting
later this year where if there wasn't a
pay phone on every second corner
that will have changed only
since 2017
right so some cognitive niches still
require that in this diagram here i
think it's interesting that when we look
at the verticals
we could probably see
the offloading the idea that why would
you need a payphone anymore
that being sort of resolved depending on
which niche you're in
but the horizontals which is really the
diacronic part that's what kind of frees
us up to go and look at a turntable
again
even though most people have got
that same capacity to access whatever
the media is
on their phone right
so i think again
i'm going to beat the same drum when we
look at these kind of representations
it's a minimum of two do we look at the
verticals and the horizontals do we see
the stacks and the diacronics because
when we incorporate the diacronics
then that looking
looking back i still probably won't go
to a phone booth
in costa rica because i just
don't need to but i can certainly
understand why it still exists and it
isn't just a novelty it exists like like
you were talking about last
live stream about why why
we've automated water access
it's still and it's there's those people
in those
cognitive niches
are still
finding those those tools useful
so
yeah i think it's i think it's
again i i keep bragging about this axle
constant character who writes these
papers but
man is he ever touching on important
stuff in terms of us
sort of being aware
not just in terms of
what we're dealing with in the here and
now but how that environment
necessarily
partitions us
as much as we actively and partition it
and so
yeah i mean go go to costa rica it's
pretty it's pretty i wouldn't
pretty modern place but they still have
lots and lots of pay phones and they
still really matter
they're in that second hump right as
we're transitioning from you know
house phone to pay phone to cell phone
they're still in in v2 there or yes some
point
where there's overlapping waves of tech
so
very interesting about
trust and glue at different levels or
types
like do you trust that you'll be able to
simply make the call
or do you trust that they're going to be
able to hear you on the call
do they
do you have trust that
you'll be understood do you have trust
that that will
have action like if you call an
emergency hotline number
that's like um
it's probably a bunch of
active jokes that one can imagine
because one is providing a sense
stimuli for that operator
so that they undertake some action and
you trust
that a certain kind of action will be
taken
though not directly knowing all the
details like we may not understand how
an ambulance gets called or where the
location of the ambulance are but then
we expect that
upon a certain type of signal a call
that one will be
arriving shortly
so that is very
interesting and then also dean like you
said we're we're partitioning technology
like
if you install linux on a computer and
it's the disk partition and there's so
many times where
technology is about
partitioning
and about putting the technology in the
box and technology is often in a box
it's like wrapped in a box and then it's
in like another plastic box or a metal
box
but then
that actually changes our cognitive
partitioning
and then we've explored in this paper a
sort of low bar
and then a high bar
where more is different and the low bar
was the offloading
was where the technology is going to
merely remind you of something and so
the
offloading
can
be freeing up
cognitive
thought cycles
and allowing for future epistemic action
writing something down on the post-it
and putting it on the doorway and it
says get milk or it's yellow and you
know that yellow means get milk but
you're offloading it to this sort of
relatively passive
more like a crossbow more like a
skateboard kind of technology
what starts to happen when technology
becomes adaptive and anticipatory
and so we are not just offloading
that's the low bar but we're uploading
and there's an active entity on both
sides of the table now and they're
anticipating and expecting each other
what is happening when our technology
use and modifications in the niche
change our cognitive partitioning
i got a question maybe for both of you
so
um
in that in that
in under that sort of the spirit of what
you're just saying
daniel so you get some you get some
platforms where you want to do some
uh you want to take all your photos and
all your images from your holiday and
you you make an imovie
or you go to final cut pro
now both of those platforms
perform
essentially the same
function in terms of you being able to
stitch together
a bunch of images but the
imovie
in its effort to be adaptive
says
how how
much of this would you like me to do
would you like me to sink the music for
you would you like me to apply the ken
burns effect whereas the final cut pro
the assumption is that you have a much
a much more um
control
aspect of this in terms of what you
want to be able to
fine tune and continue to operate
so i think it's interesting the the
technology question and the environment
question because
it can guess it can be framed as freeing
up
but i think at some time at some point
we have to ask whether it's option
removing
because it's trying to help us
but it's not necessarily generating more
possibilities
which is again another form of
optimization optimization isn't always
removing uncertainty lots and tots times
optimization is having more
possibilities
that are that are valid that are viable
and that's the harder of those two
things to determine which what's a
viable alternative here as opposed to am
i getting closer and closer to being
able to regenerate the copy
it makes me think about optimization
when we're in
the world of figure one
and when we're in the world of figure
two so human on the bike
and optimizing has to do with like speed
on the bike
okay but now we're in figure 2 world and
we're all going on a walk together like
the three of us
what is the optimum speed
it may have some of the same
considerations as the bicycle like we
want to get there we want to be safe
we don't want to break anything
but then there is this
relational layer where the optimum speed
may be a pure group decision
and um
then
what you said about optimization
how is optimization related to
reducing uncertainty
as well as or in what cases reducing
options which can be a one way to reduce
uncertainty
like you have
equal uncertainty about 100 options
let's just reduce it to two you're still
uncertain but there's only two options
but then you also mentioned adding more
options and of what kind so let's think
about choosing a cereal
so there's 100 cereals there in the
store
and we're in the figure one world it's
just the dead cereals and they are uh
passive recipients of our action
selection maybe they're wiggling around
a little bit on the shelves trying to
escape but basically they're dead and
we're taking adaptive decisions
and so there can be uncertainty about
which actions to take
so yes we could increase our precision
by having for for example fewer
alternatives
but then again you said what about
optimization via more
acceptable
alternatives what if there was a friend
or a parent or
a adaptive computer system that said
would you like me to make some
suggestions
that's actually another option of a
totally different type than serial 1
through 100. so you've added another
option another affordance for action
and in doing so it's part of a
trajectory
that does minimize free energy and
find some sort of
satisficing solution
or like
can i ask a question
it's actually an opportunity for an
open-endedness
it puts a new affordance on the table
when the adaptive entity asks like
okay could i make a suggestion about
your serial choice
yes
are you interested in this or that like
it's actually adding more
uncertainty about potentially even a
novel introduction
of now there's this dialogue it's like
wait i thought we were choosing a serial
why are we now engaging in dialogue
but then
it could be on the path
to selecting
a good cereal
can i just quote some you just reminded
me of something in the paper under the
diet chronic cognition and the eai and
the 314.
i'll just read it because i think it's
it spot on to what you were just
describing cognitive assemblies are
formed and maintained
diachronically
beyond the local organism's center
boundaries of individuals kirchoff
malophorus and stotts
cognitive assemblies are decentralized
systems
or
networks of human and non-human agencies
which is what you were just describing
the tour 1993 whose cause of
constitutive relationship
depends upon self-organized processes
distributed across
the network that they constitute
so yeah i mean i think the authors would
agree with what you were just describing
who i remember reading that the first
time and thinking to myself
again of paul khan's
book the origins of order so you have
you have
assemblies within and then you have
access assemblies in terms of a larger
energy package a constitution
and so how does that
how does that ebb and flow relative to
your own homeostatic and allostatic
um
heuristics that you're following right
so
yeah
but that's again back to the witness
piece right
i don't know if this is exactly
how to say it but
i see this
paper and
line of research and thinking
as
being sort of the upswing of thinking
about 4e cognition extended enacted
embedded etc etc etc
what does it look like to be on the
upswing
of taking 4e cognition as a starting
point
so no longer does non 4e have to be
straw person or discussed pejoratively
like
car companies today are not
doing slam pieces on horses
there's a recognized
place in time for people who are horses
and it's now in a different tech
vertical than people who are now doing
the differentiation between different
cars that they might like to buy
when a technology actually does threaten
it
like hey maybe you don't need to own a
car maybe there's going to be something
you can trust on that will take you
where you need to go
that is where you start to see the
threatening and the responses and things
like that when there actually is a
possibility to have a technological
replacement
but
there isn't a
attack
on
non-extended non-embedded non-encultured
cognition the paper does not spend a
massive amount of time describing that
cultural priors influence cognitive
processes of individuals
it in descriptive
indescriptive
and
concise
positive language
it is
recouping
and restating
an extended perspective
and taking that as a
starting point for moving forward and
for modeling kinds of systems that
previously had ineffective
or incomplete models
because
hardly could it be said that this paper
answers
anything about extended cognitive
process
in fact we keep on coming back to the
figure one figure two equation two
equation four
step
because it's subtle
but it is the contribution of this paper
because they took
active inference
which was always framed this way
extended it and showed well actually
like this is a special case figure one
of active inference was a special case
of where there could be a more
adaptive entity on the other side
and then that becomes reabsorbed into
active inference
and is a starting point for
what i hope that we'll continue to
discuss in
some of the rest of this discussion
what is active inference and extended
active inference particularly as a
starting point look like rather than
well we've done all of these
um attack ads versus earlier models of
cybernetics or of ecological psychology
we we've decimated the opposition and
now the only model that you can go
forward with is active or is extended
cognition people who don't believe in
extended cognition just what are they
thinking about like
that isn't where our
regime of attention or linguistics is to
let the record show
so what does it look like when we
actually do
start to take steps forward
in this
figure two kind of world
dean
and i ask a question on that then
would it not make sense
to at least momentarily suspend many of
the typical hierarchies that we apply
like we can keep things nested
those things continue to exist but
isn't it is an extended active inference
asking us
to start from a place of not knowing i i
mentioned this in the last livestream
i mean if both people are willing to
take that risk and face down that
consequence or if the entire
if the entire audience
has taken on that risk
and taken that that
that question on collectively is that
not the beginning of extended active
influence where now the environment
access the scrutinizer as opposed to oh
there's somebody who now judges all
people who don't believe in acting
extended active inference as being
not legitimate like it is the first
thing that we have to do is allow the
environment to be the
scrutinizer as opposed to
somebody else who's given that
role
and i'm i'm sincerely asking that
question i'm not questioning whether
that's even possible but if if we're
going to start down that road of
applying
extended active inference
then who who's the judge here
and for how
long if it's extended
it's extended active inference as
opposed to mere activities
blue you have a thought or all
go
okay
um it makes me look in the bottom right
corner of our video or act infer serve
as we sometimes do
and
uh before
the action potentially there's like this
stop wait listen perceive
that is silence and it's important to
also recognize like a silence before and
after a word
so
where the action perception loop begins
and ends
no one else
but you said what happens when we start
with not knowing what if we start or
intend for the environment to be the
scrutinizer
how
do we let the environment be the
scrutinizer whether it's short long
transient
we have to act
because
hashtag figure 2
our actions
are the observations of the environment
so if we withhold action
or act in a way that the scrutinizer
is going to get the wrong impressions
from like we're the adversarial demon
it's like oh i prefer lower co2 but then
t he i'm just putting a ton out
what could one
ask the environment to make its
inferences on only the markov blanket
only the holograph
only the quantum experiment
and so
action
is how we allow the environment to
make inferences
like
two people i don't know operating on a
saw for a tree
one person's pushing while the other one
is pulling
what are the consequences of our actions
we don't know but we have expectations
preferences and we reduce our
uncertainty about all of that
but
when we don't know which is to say our
cognitive process
doesn't have
precision
and precision could also be a false
belief
so we have
not knowing
in our non-extended active
in our cognitive process
do we
infer first
and wait until we have higher precision
which again can be a false perception
and then
that is actually implicitly putting one
into the position of the central
scrutinizer
it's like saying when i'm ready to act
then i'll act
but i'm going to wait until then these
are all of course
simplifications and i know there's
counter examples that people can think
of and that's rich and those counter
examples are in a yes and spirit because
these are only
some of the actions that i or you could
take
but
when we
empower the environment
that doesn't mean that we don't
act right
it doesn't know does it not mean we
interact more and
we we get out more often
isn't that the first
isn't that the first assumption if we
actually want the environment to become
more
involved in whatever it is
whatever the joint self-evidencing is
don't we have to actually allow
the environment in by getting out more
and interacting more
blue
so
i kind of find this like
if a tree falls in the forest and no one
heard it did the tree really fall
um
so
if there's no action
um and i guess a tree falling down is
also a tree doing action maybe whether
it's you know
your active inference or not doesn't
really matter
but but i i do think that that um
you know something has to happen for the
environment to perceive it otherwise
what is the environment
receiving
yeah so i think we're i think we're
navigating on it
but i think it's hard for us to perceive
in our minds how it might be navigating
on us
i mean we pick ourselves up put
ourselves on an airplane and fly
somewhere so that's pretty that's pretty
easy to track
but i don't know that we necessarily
know until we bump into that pay phone
in that foreign niche
how that's going to necessarily navigate
on us
we don't know until we until we actually
put ourselves in that position and then
decide what that interaction will or
will not be do i take a picture of it
because whoa i just found something i
haven't seen in a long time or to
actually pick it up
and do some and have its affordances
play on me
that's the harder part to get your mind
around it seems like it's imaginable and
philosophical but it's really
navigational and way finding and and
reorienting updating updating update
so can i just respond really quick um
i think that you are
dealing with or
thinking about when you're thinking
about cognitive uploading and this has
like been consistent through this stream
and the last stream you're talking about
putting yourself in a foreign
environment right so like i would have
to
act by leaving my office getting on a
plane arriving in switzerland and
getting off the plane and now i'm in a
foreign environment right and so what do
i perceive in this foreign or in this
novel environment but but simply the act
of moving from a familiar environment to
a novel environment is also an action
right
it's an epistemic foraging action to
be in a new informational niche
to jump into a new paper to listen to a
live stream that somebody might not
otherwise like take a little journey
with us
and it is definitely one of the
most important kinds of action
to study
just like they bring up epistemic
actions at the end of this paper like
knowing where to look like what what is
on um you know page 50 of this book
one has to have precision in an action
policy to know where to look that's an
epistemic action
and dean you've brought together
the spatial navigation element
with the epistemic
aspect and then even in that example of
the pay phone we see epistemic and
pragmatic value like if it's high
novelty high epistemic value
that might induce a certain kind of
action
like taking a picture maybe um to
document it but then also there's the
pragmatics of the phone like using it to
make a call
so this type of action
to have the initiative just to get up
and to do something
and to to have bounded
modeling
and
just knowing that one will know enough
when they're in that situation or that
it's low stakes enough that it doesn't
really matter
that's very interesting so let me read
something that is in live chat so
stephen wrote
this paper extends towards the mind body
spirit environment dynamic by starting
in terms of what most active models
focus on generative models how can we
start bigger bolder
and work back in
so i'll just give a first thought thanks
for the question stephen
so
i
believe that
when steven is saying where most active
models focus on or start on which is
like the generative model of the
particular entity and the particular
entity the thing which is the thing as
distinguished from the environment
is this
that is
the blanket states
and
the cognitive states blanket and
internal states constitute the thing
like the car
of course here we would take the car as
processed and the car includes the roads
and the stop signs but
the car as a thing partitioned from its
environment
is the blanket and internal states of
the car
and so extended the idea that this is
the thing
but that it's extending
its function in a more distributed way
in a way as i think we may have even
talked about last week reifies that as
the thing
like when the person puts the post-it
note and we call that extended
organismal cognition
do we not reify and maybe even
implicitly constrain what organismal
cognition is because we're saying well
an organism with a post-it note is
extended organismal cognition so that
means that
regular organismal can cognition isn't
that so
when we go to the figure two world
we can then
ask about well
there's now a generative model on both
sides
that's what we were looking at with our
colorful boxes last time
each one of these boxes is a thing
and then we talked about how like they
make up a bigger thing together
they make up a different generative
model together
so this thing the green thing on the
right
is still a generative model so it's not
like we're going to escape
active highlighting of generative model
but
rather we recognize that generative
models can have
sub-partitionings
and that some of the cases that we might
want to think about involve like a
partitioning between what are
classically understood to be
autonomous entities and their niche and
so it's almost like
from
the
atomic active
not the quantum just like sort of the
single entity where we're gonna put less
emphasis on the niche
then
with extended active we start to
recognize the niche as an active entity
not
of the same type but of the same
structure in terms of performing
optimization
on both sides
and then that really moves us to a place
of like synthesis which is
it's just like holistic active or it's
just
it is extended active inference
but we're not saying who it's extended
from
it's just we're taking a total modeling
perspective
on all these activities
as well as
all of these activities
now with the red line
but then
what does that
make
the purple line
and what is its niche and that comes
back to the point about composability
which is like we could stop with just
the black box
and say we're just modeling the entity
and we're not going to think about the
environment as a thing we're going to
think of it as the heat sink just like
our quantum colleagues reminded us
or maybe we want to model both sides of
the table
as things
but then in doing so
we make them into this joint
generative model
so again we didn't escape generative
models we actually only reified the need
for them
because now we've made this fusion
generative model
but now we're back to where we were
earlier which is implicitly taking the
environment to be the heatsink
blue
so
i have a thought if you could go back to
figure two that would be great
um just about um what happens and this
goes back to what dean was talking about
earlier when we're talking about scaling
and where do you put the markov blanket
so here we have the niche and the
environment doing this joint
self-evidencing
um and what happens when like they're
trying to fit to each other right but i
mean we all have seen circumstances
where
someone doesn't quite fit in with a
crowd right and so like this is how like
people become school shooters or
radicalized or you know bullied or you
know we've all seen
someone doesn't matter they see their
niche environment they just can't quite
fit like a square peg trying to fit into
a round hole
um and this happens like i just was
writing about this you know last night
um when we
if we were to take an organism and put
it in a novel environment as dean was
suggesting earlier but like i mean take
a bacterium that lives in a hot springs
and put it in a cold water pond it's not
going to do very well because it's just
that's the wrong place for it to be
um and i just was really talking with
chris fields yesterday about what makes
you put a markov blanket in a certain
place or what makes things and this is
like
one of the fundamental
the bit it's the big question it is the
question where do you put the markov
blanket like where you can establish
conditional independence okay
so like i get that answer but but at the
same time
you can kind of put it wherever you want
it
so so
when
there's maladaption like a maladaptive
fit to the niche environment
does that make it pop out of the markov
blanket and what is the threshold for
that maladaptive fit
these are just the things that i want to
know
in the actin textbook and in other
sources
there's a discussion of
bayesian brain and of computational
approaches to
neurophysiology neurodiversity
psychopathology all of these different
areas
and
by integrating them
we kind of see that
just like axel's bacteria can be
doing exact bays or variational bays
free energy minimization right off the
cliff
that
hot water bacteria in the cold water is
going to continue minimizing its free
energy up until it dies
and so
um
if systems are always doing free energy
descent
where do we get to say which kinds that
we
prefer
like maybe um we need to bring that
purple line back
and what's on the other side of the
purple line is like the modeler
like we've still been thinking about
this in a very like entity
it's physical environment partitioning
but this comes back to what happens
before the graphical model gets drawn
that's the first markov blanket where
now
you and that paper
or you in that graphical representation
now there's a blanket between the two of
you
but it's almost like there's this
modeling impulse
that is not extended it's within a
cognitive entity whether that's a person
bouncing around their head
whether it's in a group that hasn't
externalized
the model
but they're bouncing around in each
other
and then when they externalize it
then when they externalize this
as a model
that is an
action it's not the only kind of action
to take but then that is um
[Music]
the zero to one step yes dean
and to both of your comments one of the
things in our program that we used to
talk about all the time is
we don't want your sponsor the person
who is essentially
taking you and inviting you into their
professional setting their professional
cognitive niche
we don't want you to turn that person
into teacher 2.0
we don't want you to have the same
expectations of that person as you have
of the person that's in the classroom
one of the things that you have to try
to do
is be adaptive and extend
what you then can accommodate in terms
of these various
formalized
cognitive niches that you're now gaining
access to so i i
i just think that that that joint
joint self evidencing part
is
is really really critical because i
think for most of us it's hard for us to
get our heads around the idea that
well i have a certain agency and then i
have other people who who have leverage
over me and they can tell me what i can
and cannot do
versus the person who goes into a
situation and says
i'm a proportion of a larger energy
situation set volume whatever you want
to call it i'm gonna and
somebody's been able to find another
person who despite the fact that they
have a lot more experience than me is
also able to perceive themselves as a
proportion and is prepared to base
update and now giving that
that relational composition
all the all the support and resources
that you possibly can
so that you're actually
generating this possibility of being
able to invent together as opposed to
one person's downloading to another
which i found traditionally even in
those
transdisciplinary
settings um which i really like
even those
tend to revert back regress
back to an average of i want to i want
to stay in my safe place i want to stay
with what i know and only share those
things that i know
rarely will you find a situation like
the one we have here
where
every single time i walk into one of
these live streams
i assume i'm going to learn
way more than i can bring to the actual
conversation and if i and if i come in
into it with that sort of humble
sense that
i i can't come from a place of
everything that i know i have a few
experiences that i can
share and say i think that this
validates
some of the ideas that we have but i
never come at it with a situation of
going i'm going to school everybody up
today
i think it's the interaction part
and i think it's the getting into those
places of
necessary discomfort because we do
find ourselves lots of times in these
papers not really knowing where it's
going to end up and you have to kind of
have the strategies and the attitude
to be able to handle that and so when we
develop that in people
what does that do in terms of giving
them a better sense of what applied
active inference really means
we have to go a step back
and say
so what strategies do you use right now
what is what are your default heuristics
when you find those heuristics as blue
pointed out
being applied in certain social settings
and getting rejected now what do you do
okay i'm gonna uh plateau on this slide
elaboration to see what this might
reflect on either of you about applying
active inference
so
now we've added in another layer so
here's the active inference modeler
team
making
figure two
model
making a model where there is
intelligence on both sides of the table
whereas here
they're making
something more like figure one
so in this case the modeler
in the more figure one like case
there's more of a tendency
speculating
for the the modeler
to just project their cognition into the
model as it interfaces with a more
passive or
non-agentic
surrounding
when we start
thinking about making models
where there's agency on both sides
then
it's like
we have that realization
that
we're also on the other side of
something
and so that is some of the
implicit
esoteric
impactful
interfaces of modeling as development
and modeling as personal and multi-scale
development
because there is a difference with
making these two different types of
model in what this individual thinks and
their thought loops
change how they act and their actions
are the environment's sense states
so it's like
there's a lot of ways to go with it and
a lot of loops of cognition and
perception action
but again it's taking those intertwined
and nested and laterally interacting
perception cognition action loops
taking that as a starting point
not as an ending point
so we don't need to talk about how it's
not that way
we need to talk about applying active
inference
so that it can be
a starting point
and it is a starting point
and we're on the journey anyone who's
paying attention is
but what happens as we continue in that
journey
are either of you gamers like do you do
gaming
i have a little bit but like as a
teenager or something but not not so
much anymore
because
like in that environment i don't do it
at all
but in in that in that virtual
environment i have a number of friends
who have picked up the
the um
virtual reality gear
and they absolutely love it in that in
that kind of an environment
they are neophilic
through and through and they want
to share that with me
i mean they want to invite me in they
want
me to
kind of join that world of playing
virtual tennis with them because
they they just have so much fun in there
so a big part of this although it's not
my cup of tea anymore the robots are um
i can see
where you can take these basic
principles of applying active inference
and it doesn't always have to be pick
yourself up physically and get on board
an airplane and or whatever you can do
it virtually as well it's just that
knowing
when those
when those conditions and circumstances
are such that people want to
move concentrically
and circularly
around a certain a certain set of
conditions where they're limited by the
number of pixels or limited by their
their
wanting to control their carbon
footprint
but again the applied active inference
part isn't necessarily something that's
always
you know i have to i have to get on the
big
big rocket and on a way to go
sort of thing
i think this does take us towards this
question of like
wanting to apply active inference or
wanting to be applying active inference
expecting and preferring oneself to be
applying active inference if you don't
expect and prefer that
fine
do what you expect and prefer and you
will
but then
what
brings one
from seeing a phenomena
from being curious about pay phones and
technology adoption in this or that
region of the world or wanting to
understand how moving a bacteria from
one temperature and salt concentration
to a different niche how to model that
or
all of these other processes that come
up
as examples or as ancillary to some of
the discussions that we have
how do we go
from that phenomena that has taken our
interest that we've distinguished that
phenomena from the other phenomena like
i'm talking about the rotating of the
hurricane i'm not talking about the fact
that the clouds are gray or that it's 21
000 feet off the ground like there's a
phenomena
not the only phenomena but there's
something
and thing ends with ing too so some
thing ing
that has
come on to our
radar
and then how do we go from that
t-h-i-n-g or
other
thing
towards
active inference
models
and that space
before the modeler has even
written down a bayes graph
before they in their journey may even
know what a bayes graph is
or a way to interpret it let alone the
minimum of two ways to interpret it
what's happening in that space and is
that
applying active inference
even if it's only recognized later
that it was
applying active inference
well i don't have much more to say on it
except the fact that i think that a lot
of us
are trained in in formal education
settings
to never actually
really apply
active inference in terms of that
formality around what we think we what
we predict
we have to do
in order to
come out the other side of that that
particular kind of formalized and
structured learning journey that's what
i know from my own experiences i mean
until there was an active inference
group
um
something formally organized around the
concept of active inference
i wouldn't have even
i wouldn't have
i would not have guessed i would have
not have predicted
that there would be
the kind of interest that we
are now
trying to evolve and support
it's this is still very nascent in terms
of its acceptance and its uptake
if we're going to talk about uploading
in terms of what
what kinds of um
what kinds of alternatives we could
we could at least give um
some consideration
too
i can show an image from the
textbook from the active textbook and
kind of
reflect on that and this is just
this is the appetizer of the appetizer
because
of course we're going to have the
textbook group
and multiple cohorts of that where we
like go through it and the textbook is
an appetizer to the appetizer and so
just
it's a fractal it's a crumb
we've been talking a lot about graphs
that look like the one on the top
and so this is the same kind of
partially observable markov decision
process written in a slightly different
um way slightly different labeling like
a three instead of a d and a 2 instead
of an a
and a b here and etc so
same but a little different
and
in this type of model we talk about like
the state at a given time s of t
and then we talk about the transitions
of it being different at a different
time point like here is the past
and then the transition to the present
the present the transition to the future
and then at each of those time steps
there's like the emission of some
observation so there's the
dynamics of the translation of the
underlying hidden state
and then there's the emission of
observations that's the part that makes
it like partially observable and then
there's action in the loop with pi
okay
that's the top one
the bottom one is clearly drawn
if we can have a theory of mind of the
authors
to reflect
some isomorphisms or similarities
structurally between this top
representation and the bottom one
and
they discuss we're going to appeal to
these throughout the remainder of the
book okay so the tops the pomdp
sequence of states evolving through time
indexed by the subscript
continuous time model of the sort
implied by stochastic differential
equations with prime notation indicating
temporal derivatives
so here x
is like the hidden state now
x prime is the rate of change of the
hidden state now
x double prime is the second derivative
so not just like the velocity but the
acceleration of the hidden state now
each of those are emitting observations
in this y prime space
but now
the b
up here
does not reflect how things change
through time
but rather
how derivatives are taken now
and so this is like time series planning
with time series inference
where should we be in five time steps
well let's explore and roll out where we
could be in five time steps
the bottom is more like a taylor series
because we're only staying with two feet
now
and then we're just asking okay where
are we now that's our first
fundamental frequency
then where's the rate of change and
where's the second derivative of the
rate of change and so we're
approximating a future
unfolding
using only the generalized coordinates
of motion
in one time step and so there isn't an
explicit modeling of any future time
points at all it's not x prime
of t plus one
this is all about the derivatives of
motion
at this time point
so
we've been having some interesting
conversations
what kind of thing
allows these representations
and
then thinking about what kind of thing
that is
and actually how different these
representations are despite being able
to be laid out graphically in a similar
way
there are more
in this
family of graphs that we haven't seen
even if these two uniquely identified
one thing and that one thing was the one
thing there still would be
other representations we haven't seen so
blue
so you're way ahead of me in the
textbook because you're a good student
like that i haven't come to that picture
yet but i think it's interesting that
when
things are changing rapidly we notice
them more
um and when things are changing slowly
we don't notice them at all
so what
what effect do the first and second
order derivatives have on our
perception like a frog being boiled in
hot water right or in tap water if you
take it room temperature water and
slowly increase it it doesn't really
notice that it's being boiled alive but
if you take it from you know it's cold
nice cool pond into a pot of boiling
water it's gonna big time notice
so so i wonder um you know does
perception increase with first and
second order derivatives
or or the sensation increase the
magnitude of the sensation or the
perception
when some things change so fast they
again become imperceptible
like a helicopter blades then it becomes
again or like a frequency that just
becomes inaudible
is it like parabolic
okay like like uh you know that we get
max perception
like when the rate of change is between
this and this and then no perception and
no perception over on the other side
it's like uh
it's like tuning in and tuning out
there's um some
wavelength that's being optimally
perceived
and then there's trailing off
so now let's go back to figure two
and think about blue like you brought up
the beginning like improvisation
now when we're doing improvisation
do we
in what ways do we
do time series modeling to explicitly
predict
how
i will be and how they will be
in the future at specific future time
points and or
if we are uploading not just offloading
what if we just have to where is their
arm
is it accelerating is it changing how
it's accelerating
rather than where will their arm be in
30 minutes
one can just say in the very short term
in a playful space
how can we just listen to how things are
how they're changing and how that's
changing and so on
how does that move from
playful contact improv into
digital stigmargy that makes useful
productive technologies
it's another question
one of those questions isn't better
it's awesome that we have a framework
that helps us address both of them
as well as other questions
what happens when we think about
offloading and uploading using the
structures that we've seen we won't go
into it today but like
we've added
this extended perspective
to
what will be evoked
when we hear about active
in the future
it's like charging that term
with more and more
ways
to relate it
like
it'll be interesting to find out
there will be epistemic and pragmatic
value in finding out dean
do you daniel because i haven't i
haven't seen this before you put it up
here today you didn't got the book but
i've just read the introduction um
do you think do you think going forward
if we're going to get to a place where
we're going to feel comfortable in terms
of
developing the conditions around which
active inference is
more easily
uptaken or adopted
or given
there's a certain confidence around
using that
methodology
to
conform
what's on the other side of the
the
yet to be observed is there is there a
monte carlo
aspect to this in terms of
just having to play out a few hands and
getting comfortable with the fact that
that takes a while is that perhaps why
the diacronic piece was introduced
and kept right near the end
where the remarks are
in in in the sense that
we all seem to be time constrained and
we want to make sure that we're getting
value for our dollar
from our
our ways of uh doing things but
if we're going to look at it from the
perspective of distributing cognition in
the globe
there are still going to be some ad hoc
aspects of this that kind of play out
monte carlo style
like you went to one performance and
then you went to the the next
performance
five hours later
would you go in with an expectation that
you're going to see an exact copy of
what you saw before and does that change
the value
of
of being
now part of that
that that collector or that const
constituted
um cognitive niche right
so maybe maybe one of the things we have
to do is ask ask ourselves if we
want people to be able to take this on
the idea of active inference and
extended making it safe for them not to
feel as though if they don't come up
with the correct answer out of the
the series of four
that
that's not the only way to measure
whether or not you're you're gaining
confidence is around how your generative
model
gives you a chance to maybe
decide who the two finalists are in said
competition still six weeks away from
now right like i don't want every thing
now to become about online gambling but
i mean there are actual things that we
can
find in the niche that are currently
there
that would give people a better sense of
what information they might may or may
not need
in order to be able to make open that
that basal ganglia or close it
because there's a lot of times we know
that we should close it we just should
not go forward
so
yeah again i think i think
it um
it maybe some of these things come back
to how much time we're willing to spend
on it and whether we see the the
investment of time at the front end
paying off exponentially at the back end
or whether we just
stick with those methods that we
are familiar with because we know at the
end of the 13-week cycle we can say
we've now accounted for
x amount of a of a of a download or an
offload or a dump
i wonder if that's part of where we're
at
blue
this is only a partial a partial
um alignment just a yes and to what you
said it's not a direct example or a
contradiction or anything but if we
think about the tech adoption curve of
cars and
advanced modern technology extending
back
infinitely
it's like it asymptotes back infinitely
when i hear you talking about 13-week
um
quarter
educational paradigm the instructionist
paradigm
which may be able to get you from three
out of ten on the week one assessment
and then we have a strategy that gets
this percentage of people to seven out
of ten on the week one assessment in
this set of instructions the teachers
get the instructions and they give
different instructions to the learners
then you said in contrast there's
putting the time in up front and
receiving
super linear
reward
and so it's like
the long phase
where
the technology is developing and that's
sort of happening in someone's life like
and then i i saw that as connected to
the gaming
question
and so
we have a lot of the tools for that
micro gaming
getting people to engage in
instructionalist activities
has been gamified
to a fine art and science and it will
become more intense in the coming years
we can expect
even if we cognitively say we don't
prefer that
so
how
do we
interact
not just instruct
in a way where somebody who is spending
one hour a week on active
goes to 10 and somebody who's at zero
goes to one
but
we don't need to take 10 to 100
probably most of the time and how much
time should people be spending on active
what should they expect to get out of
this what do people expect from
listening to live streams they should
comment if they're listening it's a
special request
they should comment for what they do
expect that would be interesting to know
because
otherwise it's us acting
without that much of a sense back from
our environment
and so that puts us more into a figure
one paradigm rather than a figure two
paradigm
even if the material
is so massively nuanced and interactive
itself
so there's definitely a law on the table
hopefully
the table is set
such that those who are
5.8 hours in to paper number 41
that they're more intrigued and
motivated by
rather than
reflexively looking for that two-minute
explainer video because some of these
ideas
may occur at a cognitive pace that is
slower than that video in its whole
and require regimes of attention that
are not amenable to being
driven in the same way
as um
addictive repetitive
behaviors in other like micro mining
educational situations
blue
so um there's a whole science behind the
gamification of everything
and i wonder if our ability to do that
in an educational setting but also in a
work setting i mean they like you know
have performance metrics and everything
i mean we have metrics for posts on
twitter how many likes do you get how
many people liked the photo you put on
facebook i mean we metric we have
metrics for everything and so we can
gamify um i mean we gamify things for
ourselves but things are externally
gamified for us
and i wonder if
it's successful and it's very successful
i don't know that it's optimal because i
think it leads to like other problems
but but does the gamification of
everything
is that like a replacement of our
preferences for just like
winning the game
like ultimately like do like you know i
would prefer to be happy
i would prefer to engage meaningfully
with my colleagues and um you know
fellow students in the class
but instead we
are like in this weird warped gamified
way that we have to like everything
conforms to that
even though it's not aligned with my
preferences
i shift like so so
the preference for taking the game just
like or for winning the game just like
takes over
your entire model with all of your other
preferences like why does that work or
how i wonder like can we active
inference that like the active inference
of gamification that would be super
interesting to just look at like what
happens is that that one preference for
just like winning ticking up a notch or
like gaining more metrics is that that
just overrides all of your other
preferences or it just like hits harder
with the dopamine or or what's going on
there right
definitely a important area to model and
it reminds me of mark miller at all's
work
on
yes podcasts and paper so people should
for sure listen to how it's framed by
him and by colleagues but like there are
the drives and the preferences on like
thirst
like blue just enacted or for um
temperature and so within each drive
there is like a pretty clear preference
like to be in a bounded range or like
more is better but then there's a second
level process
by which one is asking
are those optimizations
across domains
happening better or not as well as i'm
expecting
like is this a balanced
strategy where i just every time i get
to 98 on my phone's battery
i'm always charging it but like
then all of a sudden i'm neglecting all
this other stuff
so i'm too attentive
for example to the battery
drive
to a point of it not being any more
adaptive of a policy selection than just
waiting until it's at 70 percent most
the time but the uncertainty about those
times where you do need that 98 battery
is what
compels people to make base optimal
decisions that may neglect other drives
so being able to model that
what's called gamification
and then the other piece it made me
think about is
we don't
get to see
figure one and figure two
we don't know
what's on the other side of the blanket
if it's
mere or adaptive or what it is
and so
it's not like we'll know figure one when
we see it and we'll know figure two when
we see it
and we'll have a super super clear
strategy for when to engage in the
figure one way and when to engage in the
figure two way
it's more like
and potentially this is what learning
and applying active inference in a
personal capacity may look like for some
what does it look like to engage
with figure two as your null hypothesis
rather than figure one as your null
hypothesis and we'll have closing
thoughts with none of you having the
ultimate phrase dean please
i think i think what you're describing
both of you are describing is maybe that
service piece as gamified
which isn't necessarily cooperative
games
but that's essentially what we're
talking about so that's
and i'm glad i got it in because i hate
the final word
blue
yeah thanks it's interesting
uploading cognitive uploading
what uh
what what amount of uploading has been
done by gamification i wonder that like
that's a curious thing
for me to now think about i should be
thinking about other things but now i'm
going to think about that so thanks
um steven wrote in the chat gamification
pushes induction over abduction
favors inductive logic and playing
within the rules of the game rather than
abductive logic which i hope we'll be
able to talk about later
so the participation is tied into a
reinforcement learning paradigm that
limits meaningfulness
because it's like
if game is about pragmatic value
then mine more
but if the game includes an epistemic
and a pragmatic component it's already
opened up now what if it contains an
improvisational and participatory
element because it's not just like we
expanded the pragmatic value into your
epistem and your pragmatics
but their service
to another
and to the environment
and so maybe that is a good place
to end slash begin with 41
and we'll head into a whole nother set
of topics as we move forward so dean and
blue thanks a ton
great
discussion and great and special times
and thanks steven and everyone else in
the chat so peace out fellows
bye
bye thanks team
you